Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/carl-helman-b116bb2 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Policy
Legal Writing
Politics

Languages

Danish (Native or Bilingual)
English (Professional Working)
Swedish (Limited Working)
Norwegian (Limited Working)
German (Elementary)
French (Elementary)

Carl Helman

Head of Section at the Danish Utility Regulator Birkerød, Capital Region, Denmark

Summary

My professional experiences can especially be to the benefit for a working place of general legal affairs, general preparation, and interpretation of legislation, public administration, compliance, guidance, and or consulting, concerning tax law, bookkeeping, and auditing, in respect of taxation, environmental protection law, and or energy law.

Experience

Forsyningstilsynet - Danish Utility Regulator Head of Section September 2018 - Present (4 years 10 months) Carl Jacobsens Vej 35, 2500 Valby, subsequently Torvegade 10, 3300 Frederiksvaerk

Member of staff of the Danish Utility Regulator (DUR), Division for Transmission, Wholesale Market, REMIT*, and International Relations.

In support of negotiations and decision-making on proposals for methodologies for electricity tariffs according to EU energy law**. Involving contacts in English to the energy regulating authorities of other EU member states, Norway, and UK, and also, to the EU Agency for the Cooperation of Energy Regulators (ACER).

Involved in drafting, issuing and publising, DUR's decisions on methodologies for electricity tariffs according to domestic Danish energy law and or EU energy law.

Involved in shaping memos and presentations on legal interpretation according to domestic Danish energy law and or EU energy law.

Involved in formulating views for consultation on complaint cases for the Danish Energy Board of Appeal.

Representing DUR by attending meetings, and legal training courses, at the Legal Affairs Committee (LAC), of the Council of European Energy Regulators (CEER).

Officially agreed and paid to work overtime, 42 hours the week, from 1 June 2020 to 31 December 2022.

*REMIT is the abbreviation in English for Regulation (EU) No 1227/2011 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 25 October 2011 on wholesale Energy Market Integrity and Transparency.

**Notably EU Law in terms of three network guidelines on the EU single market for electricity, Commission Regulation 2015/1222, Commission Regulation 2016/1719, and Commission Regulation 2017/2195.

Miljøstyrelsen - Danish Environmental Protection Agency Legal Officer

August 2014 - August 2018 (4 years 1 month)

Strandgade 29, Copenhagen, subsequently Haraldsgade 53, Copenhagen

Coordination and contributions for amendments of environmental legislation and Ministerial orders on environmental permits for livestock cattle, pigs, poultry, and fur animals.

Answering questions from the committees of the Danish Parliament.

Interpretation and guidance on environmental legislation and Ministerial orders on environmental permits for livestock cattle, pigs, poultry, and fur animals.

Assessments of applications for public access according to the Danish Act on public access, and the Danish Act on public access on environmental information.

Contributions to a memo to assess, if the provisions in the field of Danish Environmental Protection Agency are compliant with EU's General Data Protection Regulation - GDPR, (EU) 2016/679 of 27 April 2016.

Contributions to Ministerial orders and to memos on topics, coherent in the agricultural and industrial fields, on conclusions on the best available techniques (BAT) pursuant to the EU IE Directive*, on categories and reporting for environmental inspections, and on public fees for environmental permits and environmental inspections.

*Directive 2010/75/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 24 November 2010 on industrial emissions (integrated pollution prevention and control)

Skatteministeriet, SKAT-Jura; Danish Ministry of Taxation, Danish Tax Administration's legal section

Legal Officer

September 2007 - June 2014 (6 years 10 months)

Nicolai Eigtveds Gade 28, Copenhagen, respectively Oestbanegade 123, Copenhagen

Coordination and contributions for amendments of legislation and Ministerial orders on digitization for declarations and control, anti-fraud, and implementation into Danish law of EU directives in the field of indirect taxation (VAT and excise duties).

Answering questions from the committees of the Danish Parliament.

Performing secretarial work as part of the Danish decision making procedures on EU matters in the field of indirect taxation, involving contacts in English to the European Commission and representatives of other EU Member States.

Taking minutes, for the benefit of internal use, based upon speeches and interpretations into English as part of the Danish delegation to three negotiations in Brussels, leading to the issuing of the European Commission's Recommendation 2009/784/EC of 19 October 2009 on withholding tax relief procedures.

Forming part of the Danish delegation to a working party with delegates from the following other countries, Belgium, Luxembourg, Netherlands, and Sweden, and a German service supplier, for the digitisation from 1 October 2008 of the levying of road user tax on lorries.

Representing the Danish Ministry of Taxation in a working party on publication on the web from 1 July 2008 of all of the rulings of the Danish National Tax Tribunal.

From the 2012-2 edition and to and with the 2014-2 edition, one of the authors for the rewriting and updating of the legal guideline for the Danish Tax Administration.

Thus the original author of the major part of the section A.B on withholding, declaration, and payment of income tax, VAT, and excise duties. Also the original author of the whole of the section D.A.12 on VAT refund, and the author of the whole of the section D.A.13 on persons obliged to pay the VAT.

Formulating views for consultation on cases for the Danish National Tax Tribunal and the Danish courts.

Legal advice in tax matters, principally for colleagues, but also for auditors and tax consultants.

SKAT og kommunale skatteforvaltninger - regional state and municipal entities of tax administration

Tax Inspector

March 1998 - August 2007 (9 years 6 months)

Municipalities of Skovbo (Borup) and of Birkeroed; regional tax centers in Fredensborg and in Naerum

Assessment of income taxation of physical persons, primarily shareholders and independent businessmen, following assessment of income taxation of companies.

From September 2003 to June 2004, officially working overtime at the administration for the municipality of Birkeroed, replacing a colleague on maternity leave, performing secretarial work for three different municipality boards for complaints, and making drafts for the mayor's letters of reply to petitions from the citizens, and being generally at the disposal for the town hall in any kind of legal matter.

From May 1999 to December 2002, assisting the past municipality board for tax complaints in Birkeroed as a secretary in the hearing of cases.

Education

Københavns Universitet - University of Copenhagen Master's Degree in Law (Candidatus Juris or Cand.jur.), Law (Jura) · (1988 - 1996)

Copenhagen Business Academy

AF Degree in Business Economics (Danish: Merkonom), specializing in the four subjects, mentioned below, obtaining the grades respectively · (2014 - 2015)

Copenhagen Business School

Diploma (HD2) single courses within Financial Planning, and Accounting and Financial Management, specifically being the courses in the subjects, mentioned below, obtaining the grades respectively (2018 - 2019)

Activity

06/02/2023, Jakob Torring added candidate to General Legal Counsel in Copenhagen Area